A Guide to the Rockefeller Foundation records, Officers' Diaries xFA118
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Downs, Wilbur G.
  - 1952 (Reel M Dow 1, Frame 933, Box 126)
    With the RF office in Mexico officially closed at the end of 1951, Dr. Downs’ administrative duties are minimized; his efforts are focused upon transferring the Malaria Investigation Office to the Mexican government and continuing ongoing laboratory experiments with DDT and regional surveys of malaria infection rates. The capacity of the Mexican government to finance and provide adequate leadership for public health initiatives is a main concern of Dr. Downs as he makes arrangements to leave Mexico for Trinidad. Upon arriving in Port of Spain Dr. Down’s commences the task of launching the Trinidad Regional Virus Laboratory: a dually funded institution backed by the Rockefeller Foundation and the Trinidadian government. There, Dr. Downs’ expertise is dedicated to establishing the laboratory; furnishing it with supplies and personnel; and laying the groundwork for scientific research. Investigation at the laboratory will center on identifying endemic viruses (e.g. Dengue fever, meningitis, rabies, etc.) and isolating the vectors that transmit them (e.g. mosquitoes, rats, birds, swine, etc.)
    DDT (Insecticide); Malaria; Entomology; Public health; Rabies; Diaries; Arboviruses; Epidemiology; Dengue; Prevention and health; Trinidad; Mexico; Downs, Wilbur G.; Rockefeller Foundation
  - 1952 December 29-1953 December 13 (Reel M Dow 1, Frame 1,010, Box 126)
    Logistical work in Port of Spain persists as Dr. Downs continues to establish the Trinidad Regional Virus Laboratory: a dually funded institution backed by the Rockefeller Foundation and the Trinidadian government. As for the laboratories research, investigation focuses upon examining blood specimens in order to determine what virus agents are present; and, thus, conclude which viruses are responsible for the undiagnosed fevers present in Trinidadian clinics. Mouse and mosquito colonies are being established for use by the laboratory and other mammals and birds are being collected as well. All such specimens are to be tested in order to determine which vectors harbor which viral agents. Particular attention is paid to the mosquito colony and the overall composition of the forest mosquito population in Trinidad.
    Public health; Trinidad; Epidemiology; Prevention and health; Entomology; Arboviruses; Malaria; Diaries; DDT (Insecticide); Dengue; Rabies; Downs, Wilbur G.; Rockefeller Foundation
  - 1953 December 14-1954 December (Box 127, Reel M Dow 2, Frame 1)
    With the Trinidad Regional Virus Laboratory in full operation, Dr. Downs and his team of laboratory technicians and scientists begin a country-wide campaign to collect blood specimens of animals and humans afflicted with undiagnosed fevers and encephalitis. Concentrating on medical—and not clinical—science, Dr. Downs and his team inoculate animals with viral strains (obtained from infected persons) in hopes of identifying the viral agents causing the undiagnosed maladies. Given the ubiquity of encephalitis in this particular time period, Dr. Downs begins to suspect that the country may be on the verge of a Yellow Fever epidemic. By investigating the abnormal dying-off of indigenous monkeys and the loss of five human victims, Dr. Downs and his team successfully isolate strains of Yellow Fever and alert the Trinidadian authorities that it has reemerged. A government vaccination campaign is launched and other South and Central American authorities are warned as well. A conference in Washington is organized in order to address the threat of Yellow Fever in the Americas and in the United States. Dr. Downs is an attendee and speaker at the conference.
    Dengue; Rabies; Trinidad; Arboviruses; Yellow fever; Public health; Epidemiology; Entomology; Prevention and health; Diaries; Malaria; DDT (Insecticide); Downs, Wilbur G.; Rockefeller Foundation
  - 1955 (Box 127, Reel M Dow 2, Frame 200)
    Dr. Downs and his personnel at the Trinidad Regional Virus Laboratory continue to survey the distribution of viral agents and vectors—both insect and mammal—on the island of Trinidad. Human, animal, and mosquito blood specimens are collected in order to identify viral agents and mice are inoculated with the viral agents so that strains may be isolated. In order to acquire human blood specimens from patients with unidentified fevers, Dr. Downs begins to work part-time at the Sangre Grande clinic, exchanging his services as a practitioner for blood specimens. In this manner, a variety of viral strains are isolated including strains of the Ilheus, Dengue and Yellow Fever virus. Further analysis of Yellow Fever consists of a Yellow Fever Immunization Study and medical analysis of patients before and after receiving the Yellow Fever vaccination. All entomological, epidemiological, and laboratory activities from July to December are described in detail in a fortnightly report.
    Malaria; Yellow fever; DDT (Insecticide); Dengue; Entomology; Trinidad; Flaviviruses; Public health; Diaries; Epidemiology; Prevention and health; Downs, Wilbur G.; Rockefeller Foundation
  - 1955 December 15-1956 December 31 (Reel M Dow 2, Frame 376, Box 127)
    Dr. Downs’ diary entries take the form of monthly reports regarding the entomological, epidemiological, laboratory, and zoological activities of the Trinidad Regional Virus Laboratory for this entire period. The reports include extensive data and observations on experiments, animals, and patients related to the isolation of viral agents, and discuss the progress of supplementary projects such as the establishment of an insectary and the collection of animal skins. Strains of mayaro, dengue, ilheus, yellow fever, St. Louis, and malaria are the primary viruses being isolated and studied at the TRVL. Surveys and preliminary data on Grenada and British Guiana are included as supplements to two of the monthly reports.
    Dengue; Entomology; Diaries; Trinidad; Public health; Epidemiology; Malaria; Prevention and health; Yellow fever; DDT (Insecticide); St. Louis encephalitis; Flaviviruses; Downs, Wilbur G.; Rockefeller Foundation
  - 1960 February 12-May 16 (Reel M Dow 2, Frame 629, Box 127)
    On behalf of the Rockefeller Foundation, Dr. Downs visits various countries where there is RF involvement or where RF funds might be of use in the future. The diary entries comprise a travelogue of the cities, institutions, and laboratories that Dr. Down’s visits and also include descriptions of the personnel he meets and their respective research. The countries included on Dr. Down’s tour are Thailand, Great Britain, Singapore, Kenya, Jamaica and South Africa. As an expert of epidemiology and malaria with extensive experience in RF development programs, Dr. Down’s main purpose is to assess the progress of existing programs; offer technical advice on scientific practices; and consult with colleagues on potential improvements of existing programs and future proposals.
    Diaries; Diagnostic virology; Public health; Arboviruses; Epidemiology; Rockefeller Foundation; Downs, Wilbur G.
  - 1962 (Reel M Dow 2, Frame 683, Box 127)
    On behalf of the Rockefeller Foundation, Dr. Downs visits various countries where there is RF involvement; where there is the potential for RF involvement; and/ or where there is epidemiological research relevant to Dr. Down’s expertise being conducted. The diary entries comprise a travelogue of the cities, institutions, and laboratories that Dr. Downs surveys and also include descriptions of the personnel he meets as well as their respective research. The countries included on Dr. Down’s tour are Egypt, India, Ceylon, Singapore, Malaya, Thailand, Philippines, Great Britain, Nigeria, Italy and Jamaica. While in Jamaica, Dr. Downs is involved in discussions regarding the future of the Trinidad Regional Virus Laboratory. The plan is to transfer the laboratory, personnel included, to the University College of the West Indies. Additionally, while in Jamaica, an epidemic of Eastern Equine Encephalitis unfolds. Dr. Downs describes this event in detail in the entries spanning his visit.
    Epidemiology; Arboviruses; Diagnostic virology; Diaries; Public health; University College of the West Indies (Mona, Jamaica); Yale Arborvirus Research Unit; Rockefeller Foundation; Downs, Wilbur G.
  - 1963 (Reel M Dow 2, Frame 847, Box 127)
    Scope and Contets note
    Now assigned to the RF office in New York, Dr. Downs apportions his time between administrative duties related to the public health activities at the RF and the RF virus laboratory. Entries describe scientific reports that Dr. Downs submits; epidemiological conferences attended; personnel with whom he has correspondence; and any institutions—both private and public—that he or the RF collaborates with on matters pertaining to public health. During this time period, many of Dr. Downs’ entries are written from the Yale School of Epidemiology and Public Health: a joint establishment of Yale University and the RF. Trips include official visits to the RF programs located in Cali, Colombia, Port of Spain, Trinidad and Rio de Janeiro, Brazil. Entries record the status and progress of the aforementioned programs.
    Diagnostic virology; Arboviruses; Epidemiology; Public health; Diaries; Yale Arborvirus Research Unit; Rockefeller Foundation; Downs, Wilbur G.
  - 1964 (Box 127, Reel M Dow 2, Frame 1,047)
    Apportioning time between the RF office in New York and the Yale office in New Haven, Dr. Downs tends to administrative duties pertaining to the creation of the virus laboratory at the Yale School of Epidemiology and Public Health. Included in the entries is a description of the agreement between Yale University and the Rockefeller Foundation regarding the establishment on the laboratory. All other entries include records of interviews and meetings; summaries of conferences and discussions had with colleagues in the field; and notes on research being conducted at the Yale virus laboratory. Entries describing Dr. Downs’ travels to India, Thailand, Australia, Egypt, the Philippines, Taiwan, and Japan are also included and summarize the status and progress of epidemiologically related research, programs, and institutions abroad.
    Diaries; Public health; Epidemiology; Arboviruses; Diagnostic virology; Yale Arborvirus Research Unit; Rockefeller Foundation; Downs, Wilbur G.
  - 1965 (Box 128, Reel M Dow 3, Frame 1)
    Dr. Downs conducts a number of medical, specifically epidemiological, surveys—regarding the progress of public health initiatives and/or research—in Venezuela, Colombia, Brazil, Barbados, Trinidad, Nigeria, India, Hawaii, and India. While not on trips outside of the country, Dr. Downs dedicates his time to activities at the Yale Arbovirus Research Unit and at the RF New York office. In one correspondence to New York, Dr. Downs indicates that he has become the chairman of the Commission on Malaria, Armed Forces Epidemiological Board.
    Public health; Diaries; Diagnostic virology; Arboviruses; Epidemiology; Rockefeller Foundation; American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene; Downs, Wilbur G.
  - 1966 (Box 128, Reel M Dow 3, Frame 109)
    While on extended trips to Colombia and Nigeria, Dr. Down’s surveys the status and progress of public health and specifically, evaluates the progress and future of RF involvement in both countries. Epidemiological research at laboratories and public health institutions are also surveyed and Dr. Down’s discusses relevant investigations in the diary entries. After returning to the US, Dr. Downs reports to San Juan, Puerto Rico for the annual meeting of the American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene. Diary entries during his stay in San Juan address relevant public health issues and epidemiological research.
    Public health; Diaries; Arboviruses; Epidemiology; Rockefeller Foundation; Downs, Wilbur G.
  - 1967 (Box 128, Reel M Dow 3, Frame 135)
    Scope and Contetns note
    Dr. Downs reviews public health programs and the progress of epidemiological research in Colombia, Venezuela, Brazil, Trinidad, Guyana, Suriname, French Guiana, and Nigeria. While the surveys of Guyana, Suriname and French Guiana address the overall status of national public health programs, the reports on Colombia, Venezuela, and Trinidad, instead, provide details concerning viral research and the growth of arbovirus laboratory programs. The field trip to Nigeria exclusively addresses social, political, technical, and business issues of concern to Nigeria; details of research and programs are not mentioned. Medical cooperation between Japan and the USA is discussed whilst Dr. Downs is in attendance at the U.S.-Japan Cooperative Medical Science Program, Working Conference on Small Pox.
    Epidemiology; Public health; Arboviruses; Diaries; Diagnostic virology; Rockefeller Foundation; Downs, Wilbur G.
  - 1968 (Reel M Dow 3, Frame 181, Box 128)
    Between January and April of 1968, Dr. Downs travels to Ibadan, Nigeria; Kampala-Entebbe, Uganda; Tokyo, Japan; Taiwan; Bangkok, Thailand; Calcutta, Vellore and Poona, India; Pakistan; Jamaica; and Port of Spain, Trinidad on behalf of the Rockefeller Foundation. Country visits include meetings with RF fellowship applicants; tours of virus laboratories and other public health institutions; and meetings with professional personnel. When relevant, Dr. Downs’ entries detail the status and progress of the epidemiological and university development programs that are of interest to the RF. On his trip to Jamaica, Dr. Downs attends the Meeting of Standing Advisory Committee for Medical Research in the British Caribbean. Details of the meeting are discussed in corresponding entries.
  - 1969 (Reel M Dow 3, Frame 260, Box 128)
    Entries for this year describe three conventions that Dr. Downs attends. The first,“Working Conference on Viral Vaccines with Special Emphasis on Japanese Encephalitis,” is held in Washington D.C; the second, “Conference on East Coast Fever and Trypanosomiasis,” is held at the Bellagio Conference Center in Italy; and the third “AFEB Commission on Malaria,” is held at the Walter Reed Army Institute of Research in Washington D.C.
    Public health; Epidemiology; Arboviruses; Diaries; Diagnostic virology; Downs, Wilbur G.; Walter Reed Army Institute of Research; Rockefeller Foundation
  - 1970 (Reel M Dow 3, Frame 269, Box 128)
    Entries include descriptions of Dr. Downs’ visits to international virus laboratories; details on working conferences that he attended in Tokyo, Japan through the Japan-U.S. cooperative Medical Science Program; details on conferences he attended that were hosted by the Armed Forces Epidemiological Board; and notes on the Annual Meeting of the American Society of Tropical Medicine in San Francisco. The following countries, and their respective programs, were visited by Dr. Downs: Trinidad (Trinidad Regional Virus Laboratory), Suriname, French Guiana (Institut Pasteur), Brazil (Belem Virus Laboratory), Colombia (University of Valle), and Venezuela (Instituto Venozolano de Investigations Cientificas).
    Diagnostic virology; Diaries; Epidemiology; Public health; Arboviruses; Yale Arborvirus Research Unit; Downs, Wilbur G.; Rockefeller Foundation
  - 1971 (Reel M Dow 3, Frame 326, Box 128)
    Entries for this year include descriptions of Dr.Downs’ administrative work at the Yale Arbovirus Research Institute; a series of lectures he gave at the Johns Hopkins School of Hygiene and Public Health; visits to virus laboratories—both with and without RF funding—in Senegal (Institut Pasteur Dakar), Nigeria, Uganda, Ghana, and Colombia; and a series of meetings that Dr.Downs attended in East Africa, Trinidad, and Barbados. Entries from New Haven include a draft of the mission statement of the Yale School of Public Health.
    Diaries; Diagnostic virology; Public health; Epidemiology; Arboviruses; Downs, Wilbur G.; Rockefeller Foundation; Yale Arborvirus Research Unit
- Dyer, Brian R.
  - 1938-1944 (Box 129)
  - 1946-1950 (Box 129)
- Elmendorf, John E.
  - 1947-1950, 1952 (Box 129)
- Embree, Edwin R.
  - 1917-1918 (Reel M Emb 1, Frame 1, Box 130)
    The diary is arranged by interview and visit. Edwin Embree is the secretary of the Rockefeller Foundation and has various interactions with researchers, staff and professionals in field of philanthropy.
    Diaries; Military training camps; United States; Playgrounds; Embree, Edwin R. (Edwin Rogers); Rockefeller Foundation
  - Y.W.C.A. Memorandum, 1917
    United States; Charity organization; Young Women's Christian Association; Rockefeller Foundation; Embree, Edwin R. (Edwin Rogers)
  - Memoranda, January 1918
    Arranged by interview and visit, this diary documents the meetings and conferences Embree had with various professionals in the field of public health. The diary includes Family Journals No. 1-7.
    Hygiene; Sex instruction; Public health; Tuberculosis; France; United States; Military training camps; Venereal diseases; Rockefeller Foundation; Embree, Edwin R. (Edwin Rogers)
  - Memoranda, September 1918
    This diary discusses malaria control in Mississippi, nursing education and the poor quality of dispensaries.
    Malaria; Public health nursing; Medical education -- China; Hygiene; United States; Tuberculosis; Public health; Dispensaries; Embree, Edwin R. (Edwin Rogers); Rockefeller Foundation
  - 1919 (Reel M Emb 1, Frame 260, Box 130)
    Arranged by interview and visit, this diary documents the meetings and conferences Embree had with various professionals in the field of public health. The Rockefeller Foundation participates in public health and medical education.
    Hygiene; United States; Nursing; Public health; Yellow fever; Medical education; Nutrition; Tuberculosis; Dispensaries; Rockefeller Foundation; Embree, Edwin R. (Edwin Rogers)
  - Conference on Brazil, 1919
    This diary details various conference concerning public health training, medical education, current studies and future Rockefeller Foundation programs.
    Belgium; Poland; Czechoslovakia; Spain; United States; China; Brazil; Peking. Union Medical College; Embree, Edwin R. (Edwin Rogers); Rockefeller Foundation; Rockefeller Foundation. China Medical Board
  - 1920 (Reel M Emb 1, Frame 489, Box 130)
    Medical education -- China; Hygiene; Nursing; Public health; United States; Rockefeller Foundation; Embree, Edwin R. (Edwin Rogers)
  - Special Memorandum, 1920
    This brief diary documents discussions of proposals, interviews and conferences.
    Hygiene; United States; Public health; Dispensaries; Medical education -- China; Embree, Edwin R. (Edwin Rogers); Rockefeller Foundation
  - Minutes of Staff Luncheon, 1920
    Human resource, administrative and office policy notes are taken during these meetings.
    Nursing; Public health; Medical education -- China; United States; Embree, Edwin R. (Edwin Rogers); Rockefeller Foundation
  - Report, 1920
    Report on Medical Education and Nurse Training in Central Europe.
    Medical education -- China; Nursing; Public health; France; Switzerland; Austria; Czechoslovakia; Hungary; Poland; Germany; Serbia; England; Embree, Edwin R. (Edwin Rogers); Rockefeller Foundation
  - Minutes of Staff Luncheon, July 6, 1920
    Public health; Medical education -- China; United States; Nursing; Embree, Edwin R. (Edwin Rogers); Rockefeller Foundation
  - Conference Docket, October 14, 1920
    Lists proposal topics for discussions.
    United States; Prisoners; Prisons; Child welfare; Psychiatry; Public health; Embree, Edwin R. (Edwin Rogers); Rockefeller Foundation
  - European Trip, 1920
    Includes reports and recommendations, docket for executive committee meeting and exhibits.
    Nursing; Medical education -- China; Public health; Europe; Embree, Edwin R. (Edwin Rogers); Rockefeller Foundation
  - Family Journals, 1920
    The family journals detail Embree's trip to Europe to reestablish an exchange of research journals, scientific equipment, fellowships and bibliographic bureaus.
    Public health; World War I; Europe; Rockefeller Foundation; Embree, Edwin R. (Edwin Rogers)
  - Docket of Business, 1920
    Brief diary detailing Rockefeller Foundation supplying European schools with medical journals and scientific equipment as well as nurse training.
    Public health; Nursing; Medical education -- China; Europe; Rockefeller Foundation; Embree, Edwin R. (Edwin Rogers)
  - Report on Vienna, 1920
    Arranged by interview and visit, this diary documents the meetings and conferences Embree had with various professionals in the field of public health. The Rockefeller Foundation participates in funding public health and medical education. Scientific journals and equipment exchange with Europe is detailed as well as World War I reconstruction, surveys of medical facilities and education, and vital statistics.
    Europe; Tuberculosis; Austria; Venereal diseases; Hospitals; Public health; Infant -- Mortality; World War I; Rockefeller Foundation; Embree, Edwin R. (Edwin Rogers); American Red Cross
  - Trip to Europe, 1920
    Tuberculosis; Public health; Medical education -- China; Venereal diseases; Typhus fever; France; Europe; Libraries; Czechoslovakia; Croatia; Poland; Germany; Austria; Switzerland; Serbia; Hungary; Embree, Edwin R. (Edwin Rogers); Rockefeller Foundation
  - Exhibits, 1920
    These exhibits detail feeding programs, infant mortality, American relief agencies in Europe and European applications that the Rockefeller Foundation had declined.
    Europe; Serbia; Germany; Embree, Edwin R. (Edwin Rogers); Rockefeller Foundation; Hoover, Herbert
  - 1921 (Reel M Emb 1, Frame 641, Box 130)
    United States; Public health; Medical education; Rockefeller Foundation; Embree, Edwin R. (Edwin Rogers)
  - Conference Docket, 1921
    Brief docket concerning various proposals for Rockefeller Foundation funding.
    United States; Medical education; Public health; Embree, Edwin R. (Edwin Rogers); Curie, Marie; Rockefeller Foundation
  - Trip to China, 1921
    Arranged by interview and visit, this diary documents the meetings and conferences Embree had with various professionals in the field of public health in China. The Rockefeller Foundation participates in public health and medical education.
    China; Public health; Medical education; Rockefeller Foundation; Embree, Edwin R. (Edwin Rogers)
  - 1922 (Reel M Emb 1, Frame 948, Box 130)
    United States; Public health; Hygiene; Tuberculosis; Medical education; Nursing; Embree, Edwin R. (Edwin Rogers); Rockefeller Foundation
  - Memos, 1921-1922
    These memos contain notes on various conferences of Rockefeller Foundation proposed research and aid including program expansion, journal exchange, nursing education and building construction.
    Europe; China; Japan; East Asia; Public health; Hygiene; Nursing; United States; Dispensaries; Hospitals; Medical education; Rockefeller Foundation; Embree, Edwin R. (Edwin Rogers)
  - Memoranda, 1922
    Arranged by interview and visit, this diary memoranda documents the meetings and conferences Embree had with various professionals in the field of public health in Asia.
    Public health; Hong Kong; Medical education; East Asia; China; Japan; Philippines; Singapore; Embree, Edwin R. (Edwin Rogers); Peking. Union Medical College; Rockefeller Foundation
  - 1923 (Reel M Emb 2, Frame 1, Box 131)
    Arranged by interview and visit, this diary documents the meetings and conferences Embree had with various professionals in the field of public health. The Rockefeller Foundation participates in public health and medical education. This diary documents a visit from the Japanese commission and a trip to Europe to gather information on nursing education, hospital organization and health facilities.